你能行得
You can do this.
第四季 第十集
S04E10: Salud
这里是沃尔特・怀特家
You have reached Walter White.
请在提示音后留下的名字
At the tone please state your name, number,
电话及留言
and the reason for your call.
谢谢
Thank you.
第三通了
Third try.
沃尔特  如果你在家  请接电话
Walt, if you're there, please pick up.
我真的想和你一起做这事
Okay. Well, I really wanted to do this together,
但是我已经听见他起床的声音了
but I can hear him getting up,
我也没法让他不看到那东西
and it's not like I can keep him from seeing the thing,
所以对不起  我已经等你很久了
so I'm sorry, but I've waited as long as possible,
现在只好一个人来了
and I-- I guess I'm going to have to go ahead without you,
给我回电话
so call me.
十六岁生日快乐
Oh. Hey, happy birthday, sweet sixteen.
谢了  妈
Thanks, Mom.
我还以为你要睡过去呢
Of course, I thought you might sleep through it.
既然都快到中午了
So since it's almost-- oh, noon,
那你生日的第一个重大决定就是
I think your first big birthday decision
吃早饭还是午饭
is breakfast or lunch.
吃薄饼吧
Um, pancakes?
没问题
Pancakes it is.
能帮我个忙吗
Okay, could you do me a favor?
我忘了拿报纸了
I forgot to get the paper.
能去帮我拿进来吗
Can you go out and grab it for me?
-当然  -谢谢
- Sure. - Thanks.
惊喜
Surprise!
这是我和你爸一起送给你的
It's from me and your dad.
很不错吧
It's pretty slick, huh?
是啊  谢了  妈
Yeah. Thanks, Mom.
很  很不错
It's-- It's great.
我可是费劲了心思
You know, I really did a lot of research,
也不知道为什么
and, I don't know,
就是看上了这一辆
this car just really stood out to me.
它的优点可多了
It's got a ton of great features--
马力强劲
power everything, solid engine,
里面很宽敞
It's really roomy,
你能载很多朋友
so you can carpool with all your friends,
而且既然你妈妈我挑的
and of course it is safe
这车一定安全
because I am still your mother.
这车还有CD播放机呢
Oh, and it has a CD player,
你开的时候还能听音乐
so you can listen to some tunes while you're cruising around,
所以
so you know what?
早饭可以晚点吃
Breakfast can wait.
你想先开出去兜兜风吗
You want to take it for a spin?
等一下吧
Um, m-m-maybe later.
我饿了
I'm kind of starving.
好吧  那
Yeah, okay. Well, let's--
我去做薄饼
let's get those pancakes going.
索尔  他来了
Saul? He's here.
坏主意
Bad idea.
这是个坏主意
This is a bad idea.
索尔
Saul.
让他进来
Send him in.
贝内克先生  我是索尔・古德曼
Mr. Beneke. Saul Goodman.
多谢你过来
Thank you for coming down.
你好
Yeah. Hi.
请坐
Have a seat, please.
我
I--
我不知道为什么要过来
I don't really understand why I'm here.
和我的债主有关系吗
Is it something to do with my creditors?
债主  不是
Creditors? No.
我就直说了
I'll cut right to the chase.
贝内克先生  我有一个坏消息
Mr. Beneke, I have some bad news.
最近都是坏消息
Nothing but, lately.
你的姨姥姥波吉特去世了
Your great-aunt Birgit passed away.
抱歉  谁
I'm sorry, who?
她八年前
Apparently, she passed away in Diekirch, Luxembourg,
在卢森堡迪基希区去世
and this was, wow, eight years ago.
我还以为你和她很亲呢
I just assumed you two were close,
这么看来的话
given that--
也许这是个好消息
Well, maybe this is good news.
波吉特留下一笔客观的遗产
Birgit left behind a sizable estate,
而你是主要受益人
of which you, Mr. Beneke, are the primary beneficiary.
-什么   -没错  她好像没有直系亲属
-What?   -Yeah, well, seems she had no immediate relatives,
所以在欧洲保管她遗产的人
so the estate's just been sitting
一直在寻找她的继承人
while the folks over in the EU searched for a living heir.
我不知道有亲戚住在卢森堡
I don't know of any relatives in Luxembourg,
更不会有人在遗嘱中提到我了
definitely no one who would name me in their will.
好吧
Well...
你看
Ah, here you go.
她没有留下遗嘱
She left no will,
所以才花了这么长时间
so that's probably why it took so long.
他们查到你父亲
They traced the inheritance through to your father,
但他已经去世了
but his having passed--
节哀顺变
my condolences--
那么现在你就是继承人
you are the next in line to the tune of
总共是621552.33美元
$621,552.33.
伊兰迪奥先生什么时候到
让我们先看看他是怎么制毒的
谁是制毒师
这是个玩笑么
他问你是不是制毒师
He's asking if you are the chemist.
我是其中之一
I'm one of them.
好了  互相都认识了
开始工作吧
苯乙酸在哪
Where's the phenylacetic acid?
请带他去拿苯乙酸
我们都是自己合成的
所有的原料都在这里
他们都是自己合成的
They synthesize their own.
什么
What?
我不  我不会做
I don't-- I don't do that.
有什么问题吗
听着  我都是从
Look, I get my phenylacetic acid
那个上面画着蜜蜂的桶里拿
from the barrel with the bee on it.
这就是我的方法
That's how I know how to do it.
平克曼先生以为在他来的途中
你们已经把苯乙酸准备好了
任何大二的化学生都能自己做
你居然带这种外行人给我们
他说什么
What is he saying?
我们正在解决
We're working it out.
这太可笑了
我可不会让
连苯基乙酸都不会合成的小屁孩
来教我
告诉这个傻逼  要是他想学怎么做我的货
Tell this asshole if he wants to learn how to make my product,
就得必须听我的  我说的就是真理
he's got to do it my way, the right way.
我会说英语
I speak English.
那你就应该明白什么叫傻逼
So you understand what asshole means.
现在  快给我送来我的苯基乙酸  傻逼
Now, go get me my phenylacetic acid, asshole.
他需要的东西你们需要多久制作
How long is it going to take you to get him what he needs?
我不清楚
I don't know. I have no idea.
-至少几小时吧  -我有的是时间
- Several hours at least. - I can wait.
正好给我点时间来说说这间实验室
Gives us time to talk about the state of this lab.
难道你们没有卫生标准
Don't you have standards?
我是说  这地方肮脏极了
I mean, this place is disgusting.
既然这样  给我把每个缸  每个水槽
All right, we're going to scour every vat, every tank,
每个制毒工作台都给我刷干净
every cook surface,
然后我们再来把每一个
and then we're going to clean up
潜在的污染源给清理掉
every possible source of contamination,
在那之后  我们再开始制毒
and only then we cook.
懂了吗
Comprende?
你以为自己是谁
Who do you think you are?
我是你老板带来
I'm the guy your boss brought here
来教你怎么做的
to show you how it's done,
要是你就这样管理你的实验室  怪不得
and if this is how you run your lab, no wonder.
你该庆幸他没把你开除
You're lucky he hasn't fired your ass.
现在  要是你不想这样的话
Now, if you don't want that to happen,
我建议你别再像娘们一样哀诉
I suggest you stop whining like a little bitch
并且按照我说的做
and do what I said.
开始清理
这里是沃尔特・怀特家
You have reached Walter White.
请听到嘟声后留下你的姓名  号码
At the tone please state your name, number,
和您打来的缘由
and the reason for your call.
谢谢配合
Thank you.
爸爸  你在不
Dad! You there?
我在门外
I'm outside.
你还好吗
Are you okay?
我知道你在家  你的车都在
I know you're home. Your car is here.
你都没来我的派对
You missed my party,
我就想你一定发生了什么事
which feels like something's gotta be really wrong.
再联系不到你我就要报警了
I'm... I'm gonna have to call 911.
我不知道我现在还能做什么
I don't know what else to do.
老爸
Dad?
要进来就快进吧
Come in if you're coming in.
你怎么了
What happened to you?
发生了什么
What happened?
我卷入了一场斗争
I got into a fight.
你说什么  斗争
What do you mean, a fight?
什么样的斗争
Like, what fight?
你准备现在和我说吗
Are you going to talk to me here?
你在干什么
What are you doing?
我在打电话给妈妈
I'm calling Mom.
别打
Don't do that.
听着  我
Look, I--
我十分感谢你的关心
I appreciate that you're concerned.
可我没事
I'm fine.
别打给你妈
Just do not call your mother.
为什么
Why not?
因为
Because...
我又开始赌博了
I was gambling.
要是你告诉你妈
If you tell your mother,
天哪  我就会
God, I just would--
我会被她无休止的烦死的
I would never, never hear the end of it,
所以  求你了
so please...
这能成为我们之间的小秘密吗
Can we just keep this between us?
能为我保守这个秘密吗
Would you do that for me?
把它埋在心底
Just keep it to yourself.
我就是不明白
I don't understand.
你怎么会卷入一场斗争
How'd you get into a fight?
而且是和谁啊
And with who?
我犯了一个错误
I made a mistake.
都是我自己造成的
And it's my own fault.
都怪我
I had it coming.
爸爸  没关系
Dad, it's okay.
都是我的错
It's all my fault.
我太对不起你了
I just-- I'm sorry.
对不起
I'm sorry.
爸爸
Dad...
来
Come here.
别这样  爸爸  没关系
Come on. Dad, it's okay.
没关系
It's okay.
求你了  没关系
Please, it's-- it's okay.
看着我  看着我
Look at me. Look at me.
没关系
It's okay.
别哭了
It is. Come on.
Come on.
没关系
It's okay.
你生日过得怎样
Hey, how was your birthday?
还不错  你好好休息
Good. Get some rest.
好的
Okay.
那辆新车
The new car?
是你开过来的吗
Did you drive it here?
是的
Yeah.
真不错
That's good.
你喜欢吗
You like it?
当然啦
Uh, sure.
我当然喜欢
I do.
开起来感觉不错
It drives great.
太好了  杰西
That's good, Jesse.
太棒了
Yes.
干的好
Well done.
第一批货
First of many.
你说什么
Yeah?
什么意思
What's that mean?
你能留下了
You're staying.
现在你归卡特尔集团了
You belong to the cartel now.
你不能这么随便就来我这里
You can't come to my work like this.
人人都认识你
You're too recognizable.
你这张脸印在
Your face is plastered
方圆五英里每个站牌广告上
on every bus bench within a 5-mile radius.
公众人物也得洗车啊
Celebrities have to get their cars washed,
和别人一样
just like everybody else.
要是没急事我也不会来的
Look, I wouldn't have come if it wasn't important.
-行吧  -什么事
- Okay? - What is it?
我直接见了你那位贝内克先生
Well, I went ahead and met with your Mr. Beneke,
本人正式再次强调  愚蠢
which I will say again, loudly and for the record, bad idea.
嗯  但总比坐牢强  对吗
Yes, but it is better than prison. Correct?
算是吧
Marginally,
所以我才按你说的把钱给了他
which is why I disbursed the funds as you requested.
很好啊
All right, good.
不过我不信他真的吃这套
Yeah, I can't believe he actually bought it--
突然就蹦出个"波吉特阿姨"
"Great-aunt Birgit."
简直胡扯  可你一意孤行
What? But you called it.
人们对眼皮底下招摇撞骗的垃圾
I guess people see those zeroes dance before their eyes,
都能够视而不见
it's kind of like highway hypnosis.
行了  到底什么情况
All right, so what's the problem?
对待这位富家公子哥的态度
Let's just say you and I
我没有你
don't wear the same rose-colored glasses
那么乐观
where Johnny Fabulous is concerned,
所以我查了他银行账户
so I kept an eye on his bank accounts,
调出了他信用记录
and I pulled his credit report.
还是注意下上面的时间吧
If you would, note the time on that.
昨天下午3:54
3:54 P.M. Yesterday.
就在从我那里离开三个钟头
Three hours after leaving my office.
他买了辆奔驰SL550
He bought a Mercedes SL550.
其实算租的  可也付了4500块
He's actually leasing it, but he put 4,500 down.
每月还要交1830
He's going to pay 1,830 a month--
够拽的吧
fully loaded.
我意思是他甚至搞了个电热方向盘
I mean, he even got the heated steering wheel,
这又多了6300块
but that's upwards of 6,300
不用向国税局申报
that won't be going to the IRS.
就是想让你知道这个
I just thought you might like to know,
就像我当初告诉过你的一样
loath as I am to say I told you so.
他现在在哪儿
Where is he now?
嗨
Hey.
怎么样
How you doing?
挺好
Good.
你呢
How are you?
我很好  不过你妈肯定担心得要死
I'm fine, but your mother is going to be worried sick.
昨晚上我给她打电话了
I called her last night.
跟她说我在路易斯家过夜
I told her I was spending the night at Louis'.
没事的
It's cool.
你...  怎么样了
So h-h-how are you?
孩子  我很好
I'm fine, son.
我...
I--
怎么说呢
我找了些在门诊
I took these painkillers
剩下的止痛药
that I had left over from my surgery,
然后自以为是地
and I made the brilliant decision
就着点儿啤酒吃了
to wash them down with a couple of beers.
我承认  这不太明智
Not my most sterling moment, I admit,
不过我还好
but I'm fine.
昨天我真想过去
I wish I could take back last night.
你过生日  这些事情本来不该让你知道
It was your birthday. This shouldn't be on your mind.
没事的
It's okay.
怎么能没事呢
No, it's not okay.
我是你父亲
I'm your father,
不希望
and I don't want
昨天会是...
last night to be--
我是说你千万...
I mean, you really--
你千万别把我想成...
you can't think of me like...
想成什么
Like what?
我不明白
I don't understand.
我父亲死时候我才6岁
My father died when I was 6.
这个你知道吧
You knew that, right?
知道
Yeah.
他得了亨廷顿氏舞蹈症
He had Huntington's Disease.
这个病...
It's--
会损坏大脑某些区域
destroys portions of the brain,
影响到肌肉控制  会变成痴呆
affects muscle control, leads to dementia.
这病很难治
It's just a nasty disease.
还是遗传的
It's genetic.
我母亲很怕我也得了这个病
It terrified my mother that I might have it,
在我小时候就给我做了检查
so they ran tests on me when I was a kid,
不过我没事
but I came up clean.
我四五岁时候
My father fell very ill
父亲病得很重了
when I was 4 or 5.
天天住院
He spent a lot of time in the hospital.
我母亲...
My--
我母亲说了很多父亲的事
My mother would tell me so many stories about my father.
她不停地讲他
She would talk about him all the time.
我知道了他的个性
I knew about his personality,
如何待人接物
how he treated people.
甚至我都知道他点什么样的牛排
I even knew how he liked his steaks cooked--
三成熟
medium rare.
跟你一样
Just like you.
我了解了自己的父亲
I knew things about my father.
知道他很多情况
I had a lot of information.
因为别人会给我讲
It's because people would tell me these things.
这就为我勾勒出
They would paint this picture
一个父亲的形象
of my father for me,
我也总是假装
and I always pretended
那就是真正的父亲
that was who I saw, too,
记忆中的父亲
who I remembered,
其实不是这么回事
but it was a lie.
实际上  我对父亲真正的
In truth, I only have one real,
回忆只有一样
actual memory of my father.
应该就是在他临去世时候
It must've been right before he died.
我母亲带我去看他
My mother would take me to the hospital to visit him,
闻到的那种味道
and I remember the smell in there,
消毒水的味道
the chemicals.
就像是他们
It was as if they use up
用尽了方圆50英里内
every single cleaning product they could find
所有的清洁剂
in a 50-mile radius...
就为了不让人闻到病人身上的味道
like they didn't want you smelling the sick people.
到处是刺鼻的来苏水和漂白剂味儿
Oh, there was this stench of Lysol and bleach.
你能感到那味道一直冲到肺里
You could just feel it coating your lungs.
总之  病床上躺着的
Anyway, there, lying on the bed,
就是我的父亲
is my father.
他...整个人抽作一团
He's all... He's all twisted up.
我妈妈
And my mom,
把我抱在怀里
she puts me on her lap.
自己坐在病床上我父亲身边
She's sitting on the bed next to him
好让我能看到他
so I can get a good look at him...
可是他的样子让我害怕
but really he just scares me...
他直盯盯地看着我
and he's looking right at me...
我甚至都不确定他知不知道我是谁
but I can't even be sure that he knows who I am.
你奶奶一直在说话
And your grandmother is talking,
强颜欢笑  她一贯是那样的
trying to be cheerful, you know, as she does,
可是我唯一记得的
but the only thing I could remember
就是他的呼吸
is him breathing.
那是一种...一种
Oh, this... this...
空洞的声响
this rattling sound,
像是有人在摇晃一只空喷漆罐
like if you were shaking an empty spray-paint can.
就像他整个人已经被抽空了一样
Like there was nothing in him.
总之
Anyway...
这就是我对父亲的全部真实记忆
that is the only real memory that I have of my father.
我不想你记忆中的我是昨晚的样子
I don't want you to think of me the way I was last night.
我不希望我走了之后
I don't want that to be the memory you have of me
留给你的是那样的印象
when I'm gone.
记住那样的你
R-Remembering you that way...
也没什么不好
wouldn't be so bad.
只记得你过去一年来的样子
The bad way to remember you would be the way...
才是不好的
the way you've been this whole last year.
至少昨天晚上
At least last night you were...
你是真实的
you were real.
知道吗
You know?
再见
Bye.
有地方要去吧
Somewhere you should be?
只是临时的停业而已
Basically it was a temporary hiatus,
您等上两周
but you give us two weeks,
我们就百分百恢复运营了
we will be up and running 100%.
好  您商量好再联系我  成吗
All right, you talk to your people and get back to me. Okay?
谢谢  塔尼亚
Yeah, thanks, Tanya.
好  放心吧
Okay, you bet.
替我跟孩子们问好
Say hi to the kids for me.
你好
Hey. Hi.
真是意外呀
Nice surprise.
什么事
What's up?
我想过来看看  你近来如何
Just thought I'd swing by, see how things were going.
我这两天
Well, things are...
转运了
...things took a turn.
说来比较神奇
It's kind of crazy.
是吗
Oh, yeah?
我猜这就叫天无绝人之路
I think the universe is trying to tell me something.
我有好消息  非常好的消息
I've got some good news, some very good news,
正在张罗重新开业
and getting the business going again.
我想我们停业时间不长
Yeah, I figure we haven't been down long,
老客户应该还可以拉回来
so we should be able to get most of our old contracts back.
坐吧
Sit down.
谢谢
Oh, thank you.
那...那真是
That's... gosh, that's...
太好了
that's wow.
怎么做到的
How is that even possible?
我意外得到一笔资金注入
I got a very unexpected cash infusion.
可能是有人在暗中帮我
Guess someone's looking out for me.
可能是吧
I guess so.
外面那车是你的吗
Is that yours outside?
对  你也知道
Oh, yeah, you know.
总不能开辆烂车去见客户
Can't be driving a piece of crap to customer meetings.
得做出个成功生意人的形象才行
You've got to present that successful image.
对  有道理
Yeah, right, right.
这么说国税局的事...已经解决了吗
So the IRS stuff... that's resolved?
在处理中
Yeah, it's in progress.
你已经付钱给他们了
So you paid them?
还没有  不过我会付的
Well, not yet, but I will.
什么时候
When?
没那么简单
Well, it's not that simple.
问题是这样
Um, here's the thing.
我之前都没有做过正规法律咨询
I never had proper legal counsel,
所以我想
so I was thinking
我应该雇个好律师
I should hire someone good
帮我交涉出更好的和解条件
who can maybe hammer out a better deal.
不会有更好的条件了  泰德
There will never be a better deal, Ted.
条件是  缴了欠税
The deal is you pay your back taxes,
交了罚金
you pay your penalty,
你就不用蹲监狱
and you don't go to prison.
这就是好条件
That's a good deal,
我们不要节外生枝  行吗
so let's keep our priorities straight here, right?
我现在的主要工作是重新开张
Well, my priority is getting my business back
给我的员工发放工资
and putting my employees back on the payroll
让他们交得起按揭
so they can pay their mortgages.
没错  可是我想你的员工也会同意
Right, but I think your employees would agree
你应该先控制好自己的财务状况
that you need to get your financial situation in control
然后再帮助他们
before you can help them.
我的天  国税局雇你监督我吗
Boy, IRS got you on commission?
没有  我只是想说虽然...
No, I'm just saying that, though I really do...
我明白你东山再起的雄心
I understand the temptation to restart the business,
或许这笔意外之财的来意
maybe the universe is telling you
就是要你欠债还钱
that you need to pay what you owe.
斯凯勒  这是我的钱
Skyler, this is my money...
我为什么要跟你说这些
and why are we having this conversation?
你已经跟我毫无瓜葛了
You're no longer a part of my life...
而且  这也是你自己的决定
a decision you made, by the way...
我不明白你为什么要在这件事上逼我
so I don't understand why you're hectoring me about this.
泰德  这事影响到我们两个人
Ted, this affects both of us.
不  不是这样
No, it doesn't.
告诉你  你别再插手了
I'm telling you, you need to drop this.
你得在这个月底前
You need to use that money to pay your bill
用那笔钱付账单
by the end of this month,
你白纸黑字许诺过国税局
which you promised the IRS, in writing,
说你会还的
that you would do.
就这么简单
It is that simple.
好
Okay.
好  知道了
Okay, duly noted.
什么意思
What does that mean?
是肯定回答吗  我真的需要你肯定回答  泰德
Does that mean yes? Because I really need a yes here, Ted.
好吧  斯凯勒  我告诉你什么意思
All right, Skyler, I'll tell you what it means.
意思就是  我用最不失礼的方式来表达
It means, in the most respectful way possible,
门在那里
there's the door,
我请你...  你明白
and I'm inviting you to, you know--
谢谢你的关心
and thank you for your concern,
可我不想再提这件事了
but I'm done talking about this.
泰德  你以为是谁给了你60万
From whom exactly do you think you got that 600,000, Ted?
你的姑妈波吉特吗
Great-aunt Birgit?
是你
That was you?
对
Ya.
搞什么鬼
What is this shit?
我没有表决权吗
What, I don't get a vote?
我该永远留在这里吗
I'm supposed to just stay down here forever?
我答应你
I promise you this--
我们共进退
either we're all going home, or none of us are.
平静点
Now settle down.
站好
On your feet.
古斯塔沃
Gustavo.
我真高兴
你终于出人头地了
请允许我介绍我的毒师
这是你新的雇主
This is your new employer.
你称他为伊兰迪奥先生
You address him as Don Eladio.
这是礼貌称呼
It's a term of respect.
你好  年轻人
他一句西班牙语都不会说  对吗
对
No.
而且他不是化学家
这点你得知道
我不介意他是不是养猪的
他的冰毒做得比你们都好
你们还有那么多耀眼的学位的光环
而这个人
将有大量时间学习西语
是
那里面是什么
礼物吗
古斯塔沃  你太大方了
略表心意
象征了我们重新建立的友谊
我们来看看里面是什么
不是吧
蓝宝石酒
看看
连这瓶子都是件艺术品
太完美了
或许
这太珍贵了  没法分享
你觉得呢  古斯塔沃
送给您了  就该由您来定夺
我选择
喝了它
小心点
这可是好东西
你们要是溅出来一滴
我就让你们人头落地
赶紧  快点
古斯塔沃
Gustavo.
欢迎来到墨西哥
Welcome to Mexico.
你说
Now you say
"非常感谢  先生"
"Muchas gracias a usted, senor."
这人有酒瘾
要干活的话  得保持清醒
不能给你喝
干杯
Salud.
生意谈完了
把姑娘们带来
不  不  别  我不抽
Uh, no. Nah, I don't.
-来吧  -不行
- Come on. - No.
好吧
Okay.
古斯塔沃
Gustavo...
提起精神  伙计
古斯塔沃
Gustavo...
我没生气
我之前只能打你屁股
我还能有什么选择
听着  每二十年
你都得忘了你的地位
这件事上没有闹情绪的余地
你们所有人都得搞清楚
生意就是生意
失陪
你去哪里
用一下您的洗手间
可以吗
带古斯塔沃去洗手间
别让他迷路
快
别傻愣着  找把枪
Make yourself useful. Find a gun.
伊兰迪奥先生死了
他的分支头目也都死了
你们没必要血拼了
把枪收起来
安静地离开吧
你们也可以开火
然后受死
我希望能管用
I hope the hell that works.
扶住他
Take him.
钥匙
Keys.
不对
No.
好了  好了
Okay! Okay.
还撑得住吗
Are you still with us?
走
Go.
带我们走  孩子
Get us out of here, kid.